The Aladdin adventure continues...
The Return of Jafar is a family, adventure,
animation film directed by Tad Stones.
The evil Jafar escapes from the magic lamp as an all-powerful
genie, ready to plot his revenge against Aladdin.
From battling elusive villains atop winged horses, to dodging flames inside an exploding lava pit, it's up to Aladdin -
with Princess Jasmine and the outrageously funny Genie by his side - to save the kingdom once and for all.
Aladdin (voice), played by Scott Weinger.
Princess Jasmine (voice), played by Linda Larkin.
Jafar (voice), played by Jonathan Freeman.
Iago (voice), played by Gilbert Gottfried.
Genie (voice), played by Dan Castellaneta.
Abu the Monkey (voice), played by Frank Welker.
The Return of Jafar (retroactively titled Aladdin: The Return of Jafar on later releases) is a 1994 American
direct-to-video animated musical fantasy film produced by Walt Disney Pictures and Television.
It is the first sequel to Disney's 1992 animated feature film, Aladdin, made by combining the planned
first five episodes of the Aladdin animated television series into a feature-length film.
Released on May 20, 1994, in North America, it was the second Disney animated feature film sequel, after
The Rescuers Down Under (1990), and the first Disney direct-to-video animated feature film.
It also marked the first American direct-to-video animated feature film.
Gilbert Gottfried, Jonathan Freeman, Scott Weinger, Frank Welker, Brad Kane and Linda Larkin reprise their roles from
the first film, with Jason Alexander, Val Bettin, Liz Callaway, and Dan Castellaneta joining the cast.
The film received mostly negative reviews but sold 15 million VHS tapes, grossing more than $300 million (equivalent to $636,439,156 in 2024) on
a budget of approximately $5 million (equivalent to $10,607,319 in 2024), making it one of the best-selling films on home video.
The film explores themes of princess, middle east, magic, parrot, sultan.
The tone is lighthearted and emotional.